<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="instance" xml:id="INST76">
    <!--                
    Content and structure copyright 2020 by Tom Elliott (https://paregorios.org/about/). 
    Derived from "Epigraphic Evidence for Boundary Disputes in the Early Roman
    Empire", dissertation 2004, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. 
    License: Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 United States License.
    See further: https://github.com/paregorios/demarc
    -->
   <head>Disputes Related to the Temple of Artemis Limnatis</head>
   <p>
      <bibl>
         <ptr target="dbib:burton-2000"/> nos. 32 and 66</bibl>
   </p>
   <p>Date(s): <date>AD 25; AD 78</date>
   </p>
   <p>
      <seg type="instance-description">A recurring dispute over territorial control (<foreign xml:lang="la">controversia de iure territorii</foreign>) that eventually required the restoration of boundaries, therefore probably also a <hi rend="bold">boundary dispute</hi>.</seg>
   </p>
   <p>According to the testimony of <persName>Tacitus</persName>, the year AD 25 saw the appearance in <placeName type="modern">Rome</placeName> of delegations from <placeName type="ancient">Sparta</placeName> and <placeName type="ancient">Messene</placeName>, each seeking control of the extra-urban sanctuary of Artemis Limnatis, located on the west slope of the <placeName type="ancient">Taygetos</placeName> mountains along the drainage of the <placeName type="ancient">Choireios</placeName> (mod. <placeName type="modern">Sandava</placeName>) river in <placeName type="modern">Greece</placeName>. (Text <ref target="ddoc:196">
         <bibl>
            <biblScope>10.1</biblScope> (<title type="short">Elliott 2004</title>)</bibl>
      </ref>). It emerges from the terse Tacitean précis of the hearing that control of the sanctuary – and more broadly the <placeName type="ancient">ager Denthaliatis</placeName> that contained it – had been an issue between the two cities since at least the denouement of <persName>Philip’s</persName> victory at <placeName type="ancient">Chaeronea</placeName> in 338 BC. <persName>Philip</persName> had removed the sanctuary from <placeName type="modern">Spartan</placeName>control and given it to <placeName type="ancient">Messene</placeName>.<note n="240" xml:id="ftn240"> 
         <seg type="T33">Ager 1989 no. 2 = Piccirilli 1973 no. 61.</seg> 
      </note> A subsequent verdict of a “King Antigonos” (presumably <persName>Antigonos III Doson</persName>, c. 222 BC) confirmed <placeName type="modern">Messenian</placeName>control,<note n="241" xml:id="ftn241"> 
         <seg type="T33">Ager 1989 no. 50.</seg> 
      </note> as did a verdict of <persName>Lucius Mummius</persName>, apparently in the aftermath of the revolt of the Achaean Confederacy and the sack of <placeName type="modern">Corinth</placeName> (146 BC).<note n="242" xml:id="ftn242"> 
         <seg type="T33">Ager 1989 no. 150.</seg> 
      </note> In both of these cases, it must have been the <placeName type="modern">Spartans</placeName> who raised the issue with the new rulers.<note n="243" xml:id="ftn243"> 
         <seg type="T33">Ager 1989, 141.</seg> 
      </note> 
      <persName>Mummius’</persName> arrangements were confirmed c. 138 BC in a ruling by a panel of judges in an arbitration requested by the <placeName type="modern">Spartans</placeName> and delegated by the Roman Senate to the city of <placeName type="ancient">Miletos</placeName>.<note n="244" xml:id="ftn244"> 
         <seg type="T33">Ager 1989 no. 159. </seg>This case is documented not only by Tacitus’ brief mention, but by substantial epigraphic evidence: a lengthy dossier of three texts inscribed on the base of the Nike of Paionios at the sanctuary of Zeus at <placeName type="ancient">Olympia</placeName>. See Ager for text and full references. </note> The <placeName type="modern">Spartan</placeName> envoys of <persName type="emperor" rend="normal">Tiberius’ </persName>day also cited an undated verdict of <persName>Julius Caesar</persName> and <persName>Marcus Antonius</persName>, which returned the sanctuary to them. According to the <placeName type="modern">Messenian</placeName> presentation, this verdict was overturned by a governor of <placeName type="ancient">Achaia</placeName> under <persName type="emperor" rend="normal">Augustus</persName> or <persName type="emperor" rend="normal">Tiberius</persName>, one <persName>Atidius Geminus</persName> (otherwise unknown to us).</p>
   <p>It is unclear from <persName>Tacitus’</persName> prose whether this case was heard before the emperor or before the Senate. The entire sequence is presented in almost bullet form, entirely in indirect discourse.<note n="245" xml:id="ftn245"> Talbert 1984, 418 assumes the embassies appeared before the Senate. Ager 1989, 141 assumes a hearing before <persName type="emperor" rend="normal">Tiberius</persName>. At this point in the <foreign rend="italic">Annales</foreign>, <persName>Tacitus</persName> has recently introduced the idea that <persName type="emperor" rend="normal">Tiberius</persName> had begun, at this period, to avoid attending meetings of the Senate (Tac. Ann. 4.42). Immediately after the summary of the dispute between <placeName type="ancient">Sparta</placeName> and <placeName type="ancient">Messene</placeName>, <persName>Tacitus</persName>relates the outcome of a request from <placeName type="ancient">Segesta</placeName> to restore a temple, an embassy explicitly answered in the affirmative by <persName type="emperor" rend="normal">Tiberius</persName>. These two observations would tend to lend support to Ager’s position. On the other hand, the contest between <placeName type="ancient">Sparta</placeName>and <placeName type="ancient">Messene</placeName>had a long pedigree, one in which the Roman Senate had been directly involved in the past. Further, it seems surprising that <persName>Tacitus</persName> would have missed the opportunity to emphasize this incident as another example of the emperor’s growing estrangement from (and usurpation of the traditional role of) the Senate, a narrative development that is clearly part of the author’s agenda in the latter chapters of this book of the <seg type="treTitle">Annals</seg>. That the incident is related in such obscure language, without a clear attribution of context, is perhaps indicative. If this case was heard by the Senate, with or without the involvement of the emperor, to say so explicitly would undermine the carefully crafted character progression that will culminate in <persName>Tiberius’</persName>withdrawal to <placeName type="modern">Capri</placeName> and <persName>Sejanus’</persName> supposed conspiracy. The fact that Tacitus evidently had access to copies or summaries of each side’s presentation would seem to confirm Talbert’s view that the hearing occurred before the Senate. It seems much less likely that Tacitus could have obtained such records had <persName type="emperor" rend="normal">Tiberius</persName> handled the case by <foreign xml:lang="la">cognitio</foreign>. The Senate seems to have been involved in the restoration and demarcation of public lands of <placeName type="ancient">Gortyn</placeName> in AD 64 or 65, but the details are obscure (See Instance <ref target="#INST94">
            <bibl>
               <biblScope>64</biblScope> (<title type="short">Elliott 2004</title>)</bibl>
         </ref>). </note> 
   </p>
   <p>Nothing in the presentation of <persName>Tacitus</persName>, nor in the record of earlier cases, would lead us to classify this incident as a boundary dispute; however, a fragmentary inscription from the area of <placeName type="ancient">Messene</placeName> preserves a <foreign xml:lang="la">determinatio</foreign> made in AD 78 (Text <ref target="ddoc:278">
         <bibl>
            <biblScope>10.2</biblScope> (<title type="short">Elliott 2004</title>)</bibl>
      </ref>). This Greek document, prepared by a surveyor who was a freedman of the emperor <persName type="emperor" rend="normal">Vespasian</persName>, was related to a restoration of boundaries. The beginning of the document – and the beginning portion of each of the surviving lines – is lost, but the <foreign xml:lang="la">determinatio</foreign>has the boundary ending at “the sanctuary, named for Artemis Limnatis, which is above the torrent called <placeName type="ancient">Choireios</placeName>.”<note n="246" xml:id="ftn246"> The <foreign xml:lang="la">determinatio</foreign> lists boundary markers numbered 23-48, indicating that perhaps more than half the inscription has been entirely lost. </note> Although it is unclear under whose authority this surveyor restored the boundaries, the incident must be related in some way to the long history of the dispute between <placeName type="ancient">Sparta</placeName> and <placeName type="ancient">Messene</placeName> over the sanctuary and the <placeName type="ancient">ager Denthaliatis</placeName>. It may have been that the <placeName type="modern">Spartans’</placeName> next gambit was to challenge the validity of the boundaries the <placeName type="modern">Messenians</placeName> claimed for the area.<note n="247" xml:id="ftn247"> To assume, as Doukellis 1995, 222 does, that there is a causal link between the Vespasianic demarcation and the Tiberian decision is irresponsible supposition. The Tacitean presentation makes it clear that the question in AD 25 was one of control of the sanctuary – what the agrimensores would term a dispute about territorial jurisdiction = <foreign xml:lang="la">de iure territorii controversia </foreign>(Campbell 2000, 7.7-26) – not its boundaries. A disagreement over the exact path of the boundaries (if a disagreement was indeed the cause for the demarcation) surely represents a new stratagem on the part of one of the parties and, from the Roman point of view at a remove of several decades, a different legal matter. Doukellis 1995, 224 makes the further error of asserting “<seg type="treForeign">
            <seg type="T35">Par contre le litige territorial entre Spartiates et Messéniens ... a été finalement résolu par l’Empereur, en nommant le géomètre Flavius Monomitus pour répondre à l’appel des plaignants.</seg>
         </seg>” There is no direct evidence that this matter involved the emperor at all. We may hypothesize (on the comparative basis of Instance <ref target="#INST39">
            <bibl>
               <biblScope>85</biblScope> (<title type="short">Elliott 2004</title>)</bibl>
         </ref>, <ref target="#INST52">
            <bibl>
               <biblScope>25</biblScope> (<title type="short">Elliott 2004</title>)</bibl>
         </ref> and <ref target="#INST55">
            <bibl>
               <biblScope>38</biblScope> (<title type="short">Elliott 2004</title>)</bibl>
         </ref>) that a freedman surveyor of the emperor may have been assigned by the emperor, either to implement an imperial decision or (more likely) to assist a governor or appointed <foreign xml:lang="la">iudex</foreign> in investigating and completing a case. There is one case in which a governor consults a surveyor with no mention of imperial involvement (Instance <ref target="#INST77">
            <bibl>
               <biblScope>76</biblScope> (<title type="short">Elliott 2004</title>)</bibl>
         </ref>), but, unlike the other instances just cited, that surveyor is neither a slave, freedman nor <foreign xml:lang="la">evocatus</foreign> of the emperor. We must be careful not to make too much of patchy information that can be salvaged from a fragmentary inscription.  </note> If so, we may hypothesize that the surveyor himself had been appointed as <foreign xml:lang="la">iudex</foreign> by the emperor or provincial governor, or that he was assisting the governor or an appointed <foreign xml:lang="la">iudex</foreign>.<note n="248" xml:id="ftn248"> Burton 2000, 211 sub no. 66. </note> This inscription would then represent only part of the legal dossier resulting from it; there would have been a verdict as well, now lost to us.</p>
   <p>It is worth noting that this is the only <foreign xml:lang="la">determinatio</foreign> we have that is issued by the surveyor, not by the presiding official in the case. This observation introduces another possible explanation for the nature and responsibility of the affair. This surveyor may have been appointed (by the governor or the emperor) as the <foreign xml:lang="la">iudex</foreign> himself, or may have been chosen by the parties in question as an <foreign xml:lang="la">arbiter ex compromisso</foreign> without engaging the legal/administrative apparatus at all. There are no clearly documented cases of either practice, but, given certain circumstances, either is conceivable.<note n="249" xml:id="ftn249"> See Campbell 2000, 476 for a discussion of the possibilities and limitations, with literature. Campbell does not mention this case in his discussion. </note>
   </p>
   <p>The intrinsic interest of this inscription is heightened by the survival of a number of boundary markers from the area that seem to employ the same scheme of inscription as those described in the <foreign xml:lang="la">determinatio</foreign>.<note n="250" xml:id="ftn250"> IG 5.1.1371a-c and 1372a-b. Chrimes 1949, 61-67 provides a reconstructed overview and discussion of the boundary’s path. </note>
   </p>
   <p type="P32">
      <foreign xml:lang="grc">[ - 58 - ].[ - ] ὡς πόδ/[δες - 48 - ἀπὸ τῆσδε κα]τ̣’ ἄκρον ἐν κα/[ταβάσει(?) - ὡς πόδες - - · κἀκεῖθεν ὡς πόδες - - ὅρος εἰκοστὸς τρίτος ἐτέθη ἐπιγραφὴν ἔχων ἐπὶ δεξιὰ(?) κατα]β̣αίνουσιν “ὅρος Λα/[κεδαίμονι πρὸς Μεσσήνην”· ἀπὸ τοῦδε - 5 - ὡς πόδες - 3 - · κἀκεῖθεν - 18 - ]Σ̣Ο̣Ι̣Σ̣ ἀπὸ ποδῶν Ψʹ / [ - 9 - ὡς πόδες - 25 - ἐπὶ πέτραν ἐπεγράφη Κ]· τ̣ὸ δὲ γράμμα σημαίνει καμ/</foreign>
      <foreign xml:lang="grc">
         <seg type="T19">5</seg>
      </foreign>
      <foreign xml:lang="grc">[πή. - 41 - ] ἔ̣λιπ̣ε[ν], καὶ ἐνκεκομμέναι εἰσὶν κατὰ / [ - 34 - πρὸς] με̣σημ̣[β]ρίαν “ὅρος Λακεδαίμονι πρὸς Μεσσήνην”· / [ἀπὸ τῆσδε - 6 - ὡς πόδες - - · κἀκεῖθεν ὡς πόδες - 4 - ἐπὶ πέτραν] ἐπεγράφ̣[η] Ο καὶ ἐν μέσῳ Ρ· σημαίνει ὅρος· κἀκεῖ/[θεν - 4 - ὡς πόδες - - · κἀκεῖθεν - 3 - ὡς πόδες - 4 - ὅρος εἰ]κ̣οστὸς ἕβδομος ἐτέθη ἐπιγραφὴν ἔχων πρὸς ἀνατο/[λὴν “ὅρος Λακεδαίμονι πρὸς Μεσσήνην”· ἀπὸ τοῦδε κατὰ τὸ ἱερὸν τοῦ Διὸς τοῦ Ὑψ]ίστου καὶ τὸ Ὕσιον ὡς πόδες [[Π]]Ωʹ. ἐπὶ ὅρον εἰκος/</foreign>
      <foreign xml:lang="grc">
         <seg type="T19">10</seg>
      </foreign>
      <foreign xml:lang="grc">[τὸν ὄγδοον, ὃς ἐτέθη - 5 - ἐπιγραφὴν ἔχων ἐπ’ ἀριστερὰ(?) κα]τ̣α̣βαίνουσιν “ὅρος Μεσσήνῃ πρὸς Λακεδαίμονα”· ἀπὸ / [τοῦδε - 5 - ὡς πόδες - 3 - · κἀκεῖθεν - - ἐπὶ - 5 - ] ὡς πόδες ͵Α, ἐν αἷς ἐνεκόπη Χ· κἀκεῖθεν ἐν καταβά/[σει ὡς πόδες - - · κἀκεῖθεν ὡς πόδες - - ἐπὶ πέτραν φυσικήν, ἐν ᾗ ἐπεγράφη “ὅρος] Μεσσήνῃ πρὸς Λακεδαίμονα”· ἀπὸ τοῦδε εἰς / [ - 7 - ὡς πόδες - 3 - · κἀκεῖθεν - 11 - ὡς πόδες - - ἐπὶ π]έτραν ἐνεκόπη Ο κα[ὶ] Ρ ἐν μέσῳ καὶ εἰς / [ - 17 - κἀκεῖθεν - 15 - ὡς πόδε]ς ͵ΑΧʹ ἐπὶ πέτραν, ἥτις ἐστὶν ἐν μέσῳ ῥύ/</foreign>
      <foreign xml:lang="grc">
         <seg type="T19">15</seg>
      </foreign>
      <foreign xml:lang="grc">[ακι, ἐν ᾗ ἐπεγράφη “ὅρος Μεσσήνῃ πρὸς Λακεδαίμονα”· ἀπὸ τῆσδε τῆς πέτρας τὸ μά]κ̣ρ̣ος ἐκμετρηθῆναι οὐκ ἐδυνήθη ἄχρι ὅ/[ρου τριακοστοῦ τρίτου· ὁ δὲ ῥύαξ, ὃν καλοῦσιν - 7 - ὁρίζει γῆν Λακεδαιμ]ονίων τε κ̣αὶ Μεσσηνίων κατὰ τοῦτο / [τὸ μέρος· ὁ δὲ ὅρος τριακοστὸς τρίτος ἐτέθη - 13 - τοῦ ῥύα]κ̣ος κατέναντι τῆς προγεγραμμένης πέ/[τρας ἐπιγραφὴν ἔχων “ὅρος Μεσσήνῃ πρὸς Λακεδαίμονα”· ἀπὸ τοῦδε ὡς πόδες - - ἐν πέ]τ̣ρᾳ ἐνεκολάφθ̣η Ο καὶ Ρ ἐν μέσῳ· τὸ / [γράμμα σημαίνει ὅρος· ἀπὸ τῆσδε ὅρος ἐτέθη ἐπιγραφὴν ἔχων “ὅρος Μεσσήνῃ πρὸς Λακε]δαίμονα” ἐν συνροίᾳ, ἣν καὶ νάπην Κα/</foreign>
      <foreign xml:lang="grc">
         <seg type="T19">20</seg>
      </foreign>
      <foreign xml:lang="grc">[ - - καλοῦσιν· ἀπὸ τοῦδε - 6 - ὡς πόδες - - · κἀκεῖθεν ὡς πόδες - - ἐν τῷ ἀ]π̣οκρήμνῳ ἐν πέτρᾳ φυσικῇ ἐνεκολάφθη / [Ο καὶ Ρ ἐν μέσῳ· σημαίνει ὅρος· προσεγράφη δὲ Μ καὶ Λ· ἀπὸ τῆσδε πέτρας κατὰ τὸ]ν χ[ειμά]ρρουν καὶ τὰ ἀπόκρημνα ἄχρι / [ - - ὡς πόδες - - ἐπὶ πέτραν ἐνεκόπη Ο καὶ Ρ ἐν μέσῳ· ἀπὸ τῆσδε ὡς πόδες - - ] ἐπὶ κρήνην, ἣν καὶ καλοῦσιν Φαλινγαν, / [ἐπὶ πέτραν ἐπεγράφη Ο καὶ Ρ ἐν μέσῳ· ἀπὸ τῆσδε κατὰ τὸ ἀπόκρημνον ὡς πόδες - - · κἀκ]εῖθεν ὡς πόδες ͵ΑΣΝʹ κατὰ τὴν αὐ/[τὴν γραμμὴν(?) ἐπὶ πέτραν ἐπεγράφη Ο καὶ Ρ ἐν μέσῳ καὶ Μ καὶ Λ· σημαίνει ὅρος Με]σσήνῃ καὶ Λακεδαίμονι· προσεγράφη /</foreign>
      <foreign xml:lang="grc">
         <seg type="T19">25</seg>
      </foreign>
      <foreign xml:lang="grc"> [δὲ - 19 - ἀπὸ τῆσδε - 7 - ὡς πόδες - 6 - ]ΥΝΑ τις ἐστιν ἐν τῇ διόδῳ, ἣν προς/[ονομάζουσιν - 17 - ἐπὶ πέτραν ἐπεγράφη “ὅρος Μεσσήνῃ πρὸς] Λακεδαίμονα”· ἀπὸ τῆσδε πέτρας ὑπὲρ / [τὸν κρημνὸν ὡς πόδες - - ἐπὶ πέτραν φυσικήν, ἐν ᾗ ἐπεγράφη πρὸς ἀνατολὴν “Λακεδαί]μονος”, πρὸς δύσιν “Μεσσήνης”· ἀπὸ / [τῆσδε - 8 - ὡς πόδες - - · κἀκεῖθεν ὡς πόδες - - ἐπὶ πέτραν φυσικήν, ἐν ᾗ ἐπεγρ]άφη “ὅρος Λακεδαίμονι πρ(ὸς) Μεσ(σήνην)”· / [ἀπὸ τῆσδε πέτρας κατ’ ἄκρον ὡς πόδες - - · κἀκεῖθεν ὡς πόδες - - ἐπὶ πέτραν, ἐν ᾗ ἐπεγράφη Ο] κ̣αὶ Ρ [ἐ]ν μέσῳ· ἀπὸ τῆσδε κατὰ /</foreign>
      <foreign xml:lang="grc">
         <seg type="T19">30</seg>
      </foreign>
      <foreign xml:lang="grc"> [τὸν κρημνὸν ὡς πόδες - - · κἀκεῖθεν ὡς πόδες - - ἐπὶ πέτραν, ἐν ᾗ ἐπεγράφη ἐπ’ ἀριστερὰ(?) ἀναβ]α̣ίνουσιν “ὅρος Λακεδαίμονι Μες/[σήνῃ”· ἀπὸ τῆσδε - 3 - ὡς πόδες - - · κἀκεῖθεν, καθὼς ἡ ἀνάβασ]ίς ἐστιν, ἐπὶ κ[ορυφ]ή̣[ν· ἀπὸ τῆ]σδε ὡς πόδες Ψʹ ἐπὶ πέτραν, / [ἐν ᾗ ἐπεγράφη - 8 - ἀπὸ τῆσδε εἰς κοῖ]λ̣ον ὡς πόδες ΦΚʹ· κἀκεῖθεν πρὸς ἀν̣άβασιν ὡς πόδες ͵A· κἀκεῖθεν / [ὡς πόδες - - ἐπὶ πέτραν, ἐν ᾗ Ο καὶ Ρ ἐν μέσῳ ἐπ]ε̣γράφη· ἀ̣πὸ τῆσδε κατ’ ἄκρον ὡς πόδες Ωʹ· κἀκεῖθεν εἰς κατάβασιν ὡς πό/[δ]ε̣[ς - - ἐπὶ πέτραν ἐπεγράφη “ὅρος”· ἀπὸ τῆσ]δ̣ε εἰς κοῖλον ὡς πόδες Τʹ· κἀκεῖθεν, καθὼς ἡ̣ φ̣ύσις περινεύει, ἐπὶ κορυ/</foreign>
      <foreign xml:lang="grc">
         <seg type="T19">35</seg>
      </foreign>
      <foreign xml:lang="grc"> φὴν ὡς π̣[όδες - - · κἀκεῖθεν ἐν καταβ]ά̣σει ἐπὶ πέτραν ὡς πόδες Σʹ, ἐν ᾗ ἐπεγράφη “ὅρος Μεσ [σ]ήνῃ πρὸς Λακεδαίμονα”· / ἀπὸ τῆσδε ὑπ̣[ὲρ τὸν κρ]η̣μνὸν ὡς πόδες Ϟʹ ἐπὶ πέτραν ἐπεγράφη Ο καὶ Ρ ἐν μέσῳ καὶ Λ κ̣αὶ Μ· ἀπὸ τῆσδε κατὰ τὸ ἀ/ πόκρημνον ἐ̣[πὶ τὸ ἱ]ερόν, ὃ προσονομάζουσιν Ἀρτέμιτος Λιμνάτιος, ὅ ἐστιν ὑπὲρ τὸν χειμάρ̣ρ̣ουν, ὃν προσονομάζουσιν / Χοίρει̣ον, ὃς ὁρίζει Μεσσήνῃ καὶ Λακεδαίμονι πρὸς Ἐλευθερολάκω̣νας. / Τ(ίτος) Φλαούιος Σεβαστοῦ Οὐεσπασιανοῦ ἀπελεύθερος Μονόμιτος χωρομέτρης τοὺς π̣ρογεγραμμένους /</foreign>
      <foreign xml:lang="grc">
         <seg type="T19">40</seg>
      </foreign>
      <foreign xml:lang="grc"> ὅ[ρ]ους ἀντιβαλὼν ὑπέγραψα Δέκμῳ Ἰουνίῳ Πρείσκῳ Λ(εγκίῳ) Καιειονίῳ Κομόδῳ ὑπά̣τοις πρὸ ΙΘʹ Καλαν/ δῶν Ἰανουαρίων ἐν Πάτραις. [ - ]Δ̣[ - 17 - ]</foreign>
   </p>
   <p type="P29">... about (?) feet ... the peak ... in (descent?) ... “Boundary marker of <placeName type="ancient">Lakedaimon</placeName> ... 700 feet from? ... but the inscription(?) appears to be a bend(?) ... they come down to ... south, “Boundary marker of <placeName type="ancient">Lakedaimon</placeName>, toward <placeName type="ancient">Messene</placeName>.” ... inscribed with <seg type="T6">Ο</seg> and in the middle <seg type="T6">Ρ</seg> appears to be the boundary marker. From there ... the twenty-seventh (boundary marker) was placed, bearing an inscription toward the east ... ( ... to the temple of Zeus?) Hypsistos and the Hysion, about <seg type="T41">80</seg> 800 feet. To the twenty-(eighth) boundary marker ... they come down to the boundary marker (bearing the inscription) “Boundary marker of <placeName type="ancient">Messene</placeName>, toward <placeName type="ancient">Lakedaimon</placeName>.” From (this ... ) ... about 1000 feet, on these were engraved <seg type="T6">Χ</seg>. From there, in descent ... (... “Boundary marker) of <placeName type="ancient">Messene</placeName>, toward <placeName type="ancient">Lakedaimon</placeName>.” From this to ... (... to) the rock engraved <seg type="T6">Ο</seg> and <seg type="T6">Ρ</seg> in the middle, and on ... (... about 1,600 feet to the rock which is in the middle of a (stream? ... the length?) could not be measured as far as ... (of the <placeName type="ancient">Lakedaim)onioi</placeName> and of the <placeName type="ancient">Messenioi</placeName> through this (area? ... on the rock) was cut <seg type="T6">Ο</seg>and <seg type="T6">Ρ</seg> in the middle. The ... (... <placeName type="ancient">Lake)daimon</placeName> in/on SYNROIAI which also a wooded valley ... engraved in the living rock of the cliff face ... the torrent and the precipitous (ground?) as far as ... to the spring which is called <placeName type="ancient">Phalinga</placeName> ... thence about 1,250 feet along the ... of <placeName type="ancient">Messene</placeName> and <placeName type="ancient">Lakedaimon</placeName> ... which is in the pass, which toward(?) ... <placeName type="ancient">Lakedaimon</placeName>. From this rock above ... “of <placeName type="ancient">Lakedaimon</placeName>,” toward the west “of <placeName type="ancient">Messene</placeName>.” From (this ... on which is inscribed?) “Boundary marker of <placeName type="ancient">Lakedaimon</placeName> toward <placeName type="ancient">Messene</placeName>.” ... (... on which is engraved <seg type="T6">Ο</seg>) and <seg type="T6">Ρ</seg> in the middle. From this along ... is inscribed “Boundary marker of <placeName type="ancient">Lakedaimon</placeName>, of <placeName type="ancient">Messene</placeName> ... (... the ascent?) is, to the summit(?). From this about 700 feet to the rock ... to the hollow(?) about 520 feet. From there toward the summit about 1,000 feet. From there ... is engraved. From there along the ridgeline about 800 feet. From there, in descent, about ?? feet ... to the hollow about 300 feet. From there, just as nature inclines, to the summit about ??? feet. (Thence, in descent) to the rock – about 200 feet – on which is engraved “Boundary marker of <placeName type="ancient">Messene</placeName>, toward <placeName type="ancient">Lakedaimon</placeName>.” From this, over/above the cliff, about 90 feet, to the rock engraved <seg type="T6">Ο</seg> and <seg type="T6">Ρ</seg> in the middle and <seg type="T6">Λ</seg>and <seg type="T6">Μ</seg>. From this along the cliff to the sanctuary, named for Artemis Limnatis, which is above the torrent called <placeName type="ancient">Choireion</placeName>, which is the boundary for <placeName type="ancient">Messene </placeName>and <placeName type="ancient">Lakedaimon </placeName>toward the <placeName type="ancient">Eleutherolakones</placeName>. </p>
   <div type="document" xml:id="DOC196"><!--*Tac. Ann. 4.43.-->
      <head>DOC196: <bibl type="preferred">Tac. Ann. 4.43</bibl>.</head>
      <div type="edition" xml:lang="la">
         <ab>
            <lb n="1"/>Auditae dehinc Lacedaemoniorum et Messeniorum legationes de iure templi Dianae Limnatidis, quod suis a maioribus suaque in terra dicatum Lacedaemonii firmabant annalium memoria vatumque carminibus, sed Macedonis Philippi cum quo bellassent armis ademptum ac post C. Caesaris et M. Antonii sententia redditum. contra Messenii veterem inter Herculis posteros divisionem Peloponnesi protulere, suoque regi Denthaliatem agrum in quo id delubrum cessisse; monimentaque eius rei sculpta saxis et aere prisco manere. quod si vatum, annalium ad testimonia vocentur, pluris sibi ac locupletiores esse; neque Philippum potentia sed ex vero statuisse: idem regis Antigoni, idem imperatoris Mummii iudicium; sic Milesios permisso publice arbitrio, postremo Atidium Geminum praetorem Achaiae decrevisse. ita secundum Messenios datum.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="translation">
         <p>Thereafter, embassies from the <placeName type="ancient">Lacedaemonii</placeName> and the <placeName type="ancient">Messenii</placeName> were heard concerning
                rights to the temple of Diana Limnatis, which the <placeName type="ancient">Lacedaemonii</placeName> asserted was in land
                that had been given to them by their own ancestors, as demonstrated by the record of
                annales and the verses of the poets. But it had been forcefully taken away by
                    <persName>Philip of Macedon </persName>with whom
                they had fought and later it had been restored by a verdict of <persName>Gaius Caesar</persName> and <persName>Marcus Antonius</persName>. In the rebuttal, the
                    <placeName type="ancient">Messenii</placeName> adduced the
                old division of the <placeName type="ancient">Peloponnesus</placeName> among the descendents of Hercules, and that the
                    <placeName type="ancient">Denthaliatis ager</placeName> in
                which the sanctuary was located had been ceded to their own king, and that memorials
                of this arrangement inscribed on stone and the original bronze still remained. And
                if the testimony of poets and annales was called for, there were many more reliable
                ones in their favor. Nor was it established as theirs by the power of <persName>Philip</persName>, but by virtue of truth.
                Similarly by the verdict of king <persName>Antigonus</persName> and also by the <foreign xml:lang="la">imperator</foreign>
                <persName>Mummius</persName>. Thus the <placeName type="ancient">Milesii, </placeName>having been entrusted
                collectively with the arbitration, (had ruled), and later <persName>Atidius Geminus</persName>, praetor of <placeName type="ancient">Achaia</placeName>, rendered (the same)
                verdict. And so it was given to the <placeName type="ancient">Messenii</placeName>.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div type="document" xml:id="DOC278"><!--*IG 5.1.1431. See also: Pikoulas 1998, 322.20.-->
      <head>DOC278: <bibl type="preferred">IG 5.1.1431</bibl>. See also: <bibl>Pikoulas 1998, 322.20</bibl>.</head>
      <div type="translation">
         <p>
            <persName>Titos Flaouios Monomitos</persName>, freedman of <persName type="emperor" rend="normal">Vespasian</persName> Augustus, land
                surveyor, restoring the boundaries inscribed above, wrote them out when <persName>Dekmos Iounios Preiskos </persName>(and) <persName>L. Kaieionios Komodos </persName>were consuls, (?
                days) before the Kalends of January in <placeName type="ancient">Patras </placeName>....</p>
      </div>
   </div>
</div>
