<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="instance" xml:id="INST83">
    <!--                
    Content and structure copyright 2020 by Tom Elliott (https://paregorios.org/about/). 
    Derived from "Epigraphic Evidence for Boundary Disputes in the Early Roman
    Empire", dissertation 2004, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. 
    License: Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 United States License.
    See further: https://github.com/paregorios/demarc
    -->
   <head>A Demarcation in <placeName type="ancient">Macedonia</placeName> by <persName>D. Terentius Gentianus</persName>
   </head>
   <p>
      <bibl>
         <ptr target="dbib:burton-2000"/> no. 65</bibl>
   </p>
   <p>Date(s): <date>AD 119-120</date>
   </p>
   <p>
      <seg type="instance-description">An inscription from the area of mod. Vitolište in the Republic of Macedonia records an <hi rend="bold">authoritative demarcation</hi> by an otherwise unknown centurion of <placeName type="ancient">Legio I Minervia</placeName>, between the <placeName type="ancient">Geneatae</placeName> and another people whose name has been lost. The inscription is dated by a dative clause (presumably an error for the ablative) indicating the fourth year of Hadrian’s tribunician power and his third consulate. The same clause cites the tenure of an imperial legate named D. Terentius Gentianus. He is known otherwise to have served as a censitorial legate in the province of <placeName type="ancient">Macedonia</placeName>, and it is thought that this demarcation may have been carried out in that context. A rescript of the emperor Hadrian on the subject of tampering with boundary markers may have been issued to Gentianus at this time (Texts <ref target="ddoc:479">
            <bibl>
               <biblScope>93.2</biblScope> (<title type="short">Elliott 2004</title>)</bibl>
         </ref>and <ref target="ddoc:478">
            <bibl>
               <biblScope>93.3</biblScope> (<title type="short">Elliott 2004</title>)</bibl>
         </ref>).</seg>
   </p>
   <div type="document" xml:id="DOC124"><!--*EDH HD026335; AE 1924.57; Kazarow 1923, 275-278. See also: Pikoulas 1999, 899.10.-->
      <head>DOC124: <bibl type="preferred">EDH HD026335</bibl>; <bibl>AE 1924.57</bibl>; <bibl>Kazarow 1923, 275-278</bibl>. See also: <bibl>Pikoulas 1999, 899.10</bibl>.</head>
      <div type="edition" xml:lang="la">
         <ab>
            <lb n="1"/>Imp(eratore) Caes(ari) [di]
            <lb break="no"/>vi Traiani P[ar]
            <lb break="no"/>thici fil(io) divi [Ner]
            <lb break="no"/>vae nepoti Tr[ai]
            <lb break="no"/>ano Ha(dria)no A[ug(usto)]
            <lb/>pontifici m[a]
            <lb break="no"/>ximo tr(ibunicia) pot[e]
            <lb break="no"/>state IIII co(n)s(uli) [III]
            <lb/>D(ecimo?) Terentio G[en]
            <lb break="no"/>tiano leg(ato) A[ug(usti)]
            <lb/>pr(o) pr(aetore) termin[i]
            <lb/>positi per Cl(audium) A[---]
            <lb break="no"/>num Maaxim[um(!) |(centurionem)]
            <lb/>leg(ionis) I Minerv(i)ae [in]
            <lb break="no"/>ter Geneata[s et ---]
            <lb break="no"/>xinos</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="edition" xml:lang="la">
         <ab>
            <lb n="1"/>
         </ab>
      </div>
      <div type="translation">
         <p>When(?) the emperor Caesar, son of the divine
                Trajan Parthicus, grandson of the divine Nerva, Trajan <persName type="emperor">Hadrian </persName>Augustus, pontifex maximus,
                (held the) tribunician power for the 4th time, (and was?) consul 3 times (and when?)
                    <persName>Decimus(?) Terentius Gentianus</persName> (was) propraetorian imperial legate, boundary markers were
                placed through <persName>Claudius A[---]nus Maaximus</persName> (sic), centurion of <placeName type="ancient">Legio I Minervia</placeName>, between the
                    <placeName type="ancient">Geneatae</placeName> and the
                    <placeName type="ancient">[---]xini</placeName>.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div type="document" xml:id="DOC479"><!--Dig. 47.21.2.-->
      <head>DOC479: <bibl>Dig. 47.21.2</bibl>.</head>
      <div type="edition" xml:lang="la">
         <ab>
            <lb n="1"/>CALLISTRATUS libro tertio de cognitionibus. Diuus Hadrianus in haec uerba rescripsit: ‘Quin pessimum factum sit eorum, qui terminos finium causa positos propulerunt, dubitari non potest. de poena tamen modus ex condicione personae et mente facientis magis statui potest: nam si splendidiores personae sunt, quae conuincuntur, non dubie occupandorum alienorum finium causa id admiserunt, et possunt in tempus, ut cuiusque patiatur aetas, relegari, id est si iuuenior, in longius, si senior, recisius. si uero alii negotium gesserunt et ministerio functi sunt, castigari et ad opus biennio dari. quod si per ignorantiam aut fortuito lapides furati sunt, sufficiet eos uerberibus decidere’.</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="translation">
         <p>
            <persName>Callistratus</persName>, <foreign xml:lang="la">De Cognitionibus</foreign>, book 3: The god <persName type="emperor" rend="normal">Hadrian</persName> issued a rescript in the
                following words: “That an evil deed has been done by those who have moved <foreign xml:lang="la">termini</foreign> placed for the sake of
                boundaries, there can be no doubt. Concerning the penalty, however, it is possible
                to determine the magnitude according to the status of the individual and the intent:
                for, if the individuals who are found guilty are of higher rank, doubtless they did
                it for the sake of occupying someone else’s boundaries, and they can, for a period
                of time, as the age of each permits, be relegated; that is: if they are younger, for
                longer, if older, shorter. But if they have undertaken the business of others and
                are discharging a duty, (they should) be punished and remanded for labor for two
                years. But if through ignorance or by chance the stones were removed, then it is
                sufficient for them to be beaten with a whip.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div type="document" xml:id="DOC478"><!--*Coll. 13.3.-->
      <head>DOC478: <bibl type="preferred">Coll. 13.3</bibl>.</head>
      <div type="edition" xml:lang="la">
         <ab>
            <lb n="1"/>Ulpianus libro octavo de officio proconsulis sub titulo de termino moto: Eos qui terminos moverunt non inpune id facere debere divus Hadrianus Terentio Gentiano XVII k. Sept. se III consule rescriptsit, quo rescripto poenam variam statuit. Verba rescripti ita se habent: ‘pessimum factum eorum, qui termino finium causa positos abstulerunt, dubitari non potest. Poenae tamen modus ex condicione personae et mente facientis magis statui potest: nam si splendidiores sunt personae, quae convincuntur, non dubito quin occupandorum allorum finium causa id admiserint, et possunt in tempus, ut cuiusque patitur aetas, relegari id est si iuvenior in longius, si senior reecisius: si vero alii negotium gesserunt et ministerio juncti sunt, castigari et sic in biennium aut triennium ad opus publicum dari. Quod si per ignorantiam aut fortuito lapides usus causa furati sunt, sufficit eos verberibus coerceri.’</ab>
      </div>
      <div type="translation">
         <p>
            <persName>Ulpian</persName>, <foreign xml:lang="la">De officio proconsulis</foreign>, book eight, under the heading <foreign xml:lang="la">De termino moto</foreign>: The god <persName type="emperor" rend="normal">Hadrian</persName> issued a rescript to
                    <persName>Terentius Gentianus</persName> 17 days
                before the Kalends of September in his third consulate that those who have moved
                    <foreign xml:lang="la">termini</foreign> ought not to do so
                with impunity, in which rescript he established a varying penalty. The wording of
                the rescript is as follows: “That an evil deed has been done by those who have moved
                    <foreign xml:lang="la">termini</foreign> placed for the sake of
                boundaries, there can be no doubt. Nevertheless, the magnitude of the penalty can be
                established according to the status of the individual and the intent: for, if the
                individuals who are convicted are of higher rank, doubtless they did it for the sake
                of occupying someone else’s boundaries, and they may be, for a time, as the age of
                each allows, relegated, that is, if younger, for longer, if older, shorter. But, if
                they have undertaken the business of others and are executing their duty, (they can
                be) punished and thus given over to public work for two or three years. But if
                through ignorance or by accident the stones were appropriated for reuse, it is
                sufficient for them to be punished with the whip.”</p>
      </div>
   </div>
</div>
